welcome back to the show we're talking
about the crackdown on whistleblowers
and those who leak sensitive government
information in the United States let's
get back to our panel killeen you know
and Barack Obama came to office he was
seen as the great liberal hope on day
one in the office he said that this
would be a new era of openness seven and
a half years later more people have been
prosecuted under the 1917 Espionage Act
by this administration than all previous
presidents combined has this president
president barack obama undermined the
whistleblower system i would say so one
of the points here is that before Barack
Obama the legal experts did not think
that the Espionage Act of 1917 that was
passed back during World War one in
order to actually address true spies
most legal experts did not believe that
that applied that you couldn't even use
that statute to prosecute a
whistleblower who was acting in the
public interest and that is the reason
why there were so few there was Daniel
Ellsberg but there was very few
prosecutions now Barack Obama's team
decided that they would use that all
1917 Espionage Act which as Bradley moss
explains does not have a defense for
acting in the public interest it does
not actually have a whistleblower
defense to it and that is the problem if
Edward Snowden was allowed to argue that
he wanted to reveal unconstitutional
acts on the part of the government or
serve public safety etc I would have no
problem in telling Edward Snowden to
come back and face trial but I'm
sexually that old luck and Barack Obama
is the problem for using that law right
and cook if we look at how the law is
applied is it applied fairly because we
get the case of the former director of
the CIA David Petraeus who leaked
classified documents to his girlfriend
Paula Broadwell he got a fine and
probation if that had been somebody else
precisely right go ahead well I was just
going to say a good example
um you know if any of us had done with
Hillary Clinton did we'd already be in
jail there's no question look at the
fervor they use to go after Thomas Drake
and they couldn't even substantiate that
anything Thomas Drake ad was classified
now here's a kicker and why Snowden did
what he did and this is for Bradley also
a new whistleblower has emerged from the
former Pentagon IG office he was there
when the complaint we filed in 2004
arrived at that Pentagon's IG office he
has information very strongly suggestive
that senior personnel in the AG's office
gave our names including Tom Drake to
the Department of Justice thus violating
a strict policy of confidentiality for
whistleblowers what I'm trying to say
Anand is why did Snowden do what he did
because he saw the injustice and the
breakdown that happened to us and one
comment on Bradley's comments while I
understand there's no provision counting
for purpose or intent Snowden had no
time in a secure environment too closely
go through carefully all the documents
he leaked he took a chance that he'd get
some good stuff and some wrongful stuff
it wasn't an intent to spread it all
over the place and indeed the media was
cautioned not to do so and there's still
a lot of stuff that hasn't been put out
in public so I think that's a debatable
issue brettly I'll say is as far as I
recall the way edwards known described
it he went through it methodically he
took months together some it's not the
old days of Daniel Ellsberg we have to
copy by hand piece by piece every
document he sticks of the USB Drive a
USB piece into his laptop and he's
downloading the tens of thousands of
documents as far as he had explained it
dating back to jun 2013 he methodically
determined what he wouldn't would not
give to glenn greenwald and the others
now he has said he's told them okay you
apply best judgment
that this the disciple tours public
that's my but the law doesn't care the
law says if you leak it doesn't matter
if he never gets public ever gets
published that's in the ettes the end of
it well let's get back to how the law is
applied and let's look at another case
here John Kiriakou former CIA analyst
was sent to prison because unique the
name of CIA operative who was in his
view torturing prisoners now what has
happened the end result of this is that
kyriacou was punished the man who
allegedly carried out the torturing goes
unpunished it's lovely phrase called
prosecutorial discretion uh and in terms
of John Kerry aku yeah unfortunately for
him he was already probably on the do
Jays radar cuz he had gone public in
actually in CIA's defense originally
justifying the torture techniques they
were originally used he did an interview
with ABC in 2007's was already on the
radar for having leaked classified
information there but when he got
indicted it was for disclosing the
identity of a covert official Russian
not only under the Espionage Act that's
the intelligence identities Protection
Act you cannot do that end of discussion
but isn't that doesn't that go to
colleens point is you can't cover him
something illegal by saying that it's
not classified unfortunately there was a
court ruling in a for sale a camera but
the court in ruling of time I head on in
US District Court in DC a few years ago
where they challenged that idea that you
couldn't classify something that was
itself illegal they were doing this
relating to the Bush administration's
original surveillance program court
rejected that argument said no that's
not the way the executive order reads
it's not whether or not the underlying
conduct was illegal it's whether or not
the decision to classified itself was
illegal okay I want to get to another
case cooling the Obama Justice
Department threatened in New York Times
reporter with imprisonment if he didn't
testify against a CIA whistleblower that
CIA officer was charged with providing
ricin James ricin was the name of the
new york times reporter with information
let's take a listen to what ricin had to
say the government wants to crack down
on anyone who dissents or blows the
whistle or talks in any way that the
White House of the CIA or the NSA or any
of these agencies doesn't like and so
they then they they these agencies go to
the Justice Department to
do their bidding to start to try to
punish people who have spoken out that
was James ricin talking on the heat last
year he was talking to me but cooling
doesn't that send a chilling message to
whistleblowers and more especially
doesn't that tell us something about
what this administration thinks of the
media absolutely and it also points out
the double standard that we were just
talking about speaking of disclosing CIA
covert identities it looks like some of
the emails that Hillary Clinton was
holding and sending on her unsecured
private server included the identities
the real identities of covert CIA
operatives and as mr. Moss just
explained there is a law that that
prohibits giving out the identities now
what will we see here as he said
prosecutorial discretion will mean that
the double standard that in all
likelihood Hilary Clinton will get off
with a with a slap on the wrist at best
and poor Geoffrey sterling it's
prosecuted as well as many other you
know many other whistleblowers have been
prosecuted because they don't have the
power in Jeffrey Sterling's case he had
filed an EE all for yo complaint for
discrimination because he's black and
that may have been the thing that they
were looking at two so people at the
lower echelons do not enjoy this
privilege and I I think it's a sad case
sad day in the United States when you
can classify information to cover up
illegal ed and the part of the same
officials okay good I've got about 30
seconds Edward Snowden is calling for
eintrag protection for whistleblowers he
said that going to the press is probably
the best chance of whistleblower has if
he or she wants to get out information
does Snowden have a point here he does
but even that's dangerous on on we know
the NSA and other government
intelligence agencies are keen to watch
reporters and with whom they speak in
order to
ferret out potential whistleblowers and
sources of information that's very
embarrassing to the government so we
have a huge issue here that needs to be
addressed